<!-- $Id$ -->

<Chapter Label="Intro">
<Heading>Introduction and installation</Heading>    

The &GAP; package &openmath; provides an &OpenMath; phrasebook for &GAP;: 
it allows &GAP; users to import and export mathematical objects encoded in 
&OpenMath; for the purpose of exchanging them with other &OpenMath;-enabled
applications. 
<P/>

For further information about &OpenMath; standard see the &OpenMath; homepage
<URL>http://www.openmath.org</URL>.
<P/>

The &openmath; package will be most useful if used in conjunction with the
&GAP; package &SCSCP; (<Cite Key="SCSCPpkg"/>) which implements the Symbolic 
Computation Software Composability protocol (<Cite Key="SCSCPspec"/>). This
protocol specifies an &OpenMath;-based remote procedure call framework, in which
all messages (procedure calls and returns of results of successful comutation
or error messages) are encoded in &OpenMath; using content dictionaries 
&scscp1; and &scscp2; (<Cite Key="scscp1cd"/>, <Cite Key="scscp2cd"/>).
Using the &SCSCP; package, GAP can communicate locally or remotely with any 
other &OpenMath;-enabled &SCSCP;-compliant application which may be not only 
another computer algebra system but also another instance of the GAP system
or even, for example, an external C/C++ or Java application. Such communication
will go into seamless manner with &GAP;/&OpenMath; conversion going in the
background.
<P/>

To use the &openmath; package it is required to install the &GAPDoc; package
<Cite Key="GAPDoc"/> to use the help system and parse &OpenMath; objects 
in XML format.
<P/>

To install the &openmath; package, unpack the archive and place the <File>openmath</File>
directory in the <File>pkg</File> subdirectory of your &GAP;4.4 installation. 
When you don't have access to the directory of your main &GAP; 
installation, you can also install the package 
<E>outside the &GAP; main directory</E>
by unpacking it inside a directory <File>MYGAPDIR/pkg</File>. 
Then to be able to load &openmath; you need to call GAP with the 
<C>-l ";MYGAPDIR"</C> option.
<P/>

The package comes together with the program <File>gpipe</File> which should be
used to parse binary &OpenMath; format. To compile binaries, do the following:

<Example>
<![CDATA[
cd pkg/openmath
cd OMCv1.3c/src/
./configure
make
cd ../../
./configure ../../
make
]]>
</Example>

However, it is possible to ignore this step if the binary &OpenMath; 
format will not be used.

</Chapter>